Well, This video will open your eyes.
The reason is that most of us take health
insurance, but they do not know how many things
their advisors have hidden from them while
taking health insurance.
Ultimately, when you go to make a claim, you
will not get the claim and on what small things
you do not get the claim.
I am going to cover all these points today
and along with this, I am also going to tell
you that if you have not taken health insurance
till now.
Health insurance is renewed every year.
This means that in a way you are taking new
health insurance every year.
So, if you are about to renew yours or if
you are going to take new health insurance,
then you will take care of these points which
I am going to tell you, do ask all these points
from your advisor and if you buy insurance
online, then you need to check all these points.
I will proceed step by step and you will know
and check by yourself if you have health insurance,
that all these things are covered inside it
or not.
More and more people will come to know that
in today's date the health insurance they
have taken is worthless.
Now I start it, so I start with the first
point is the room rent capping.
Now, what is this room rent capping?
I will tell you exactly what happened, My
father had a minor accident.
There was an injury on his shoulder and the
doctor suggested the operation.
So when we went for the operation, I was very
young, at that time, I came to know at that
time, then he said that you will not get the
room you want, you will get a normal room
then I asked why that room would not be available
and why would we get this room, then they
told at that time that your insurance which
you have taken here has a capping of room rent
Now, what is this room rent capping?
I'll explain this to you.
Whatever your policy is and for example, you
have a policy of ₹ 300000?
What happens in most companies is that they
give you a maximum assured amount is of 1% of the room rent.
What does it mean that if you have a policy
of three lakhs then it becomes ₹ 3000 at
one per cent, you can take a room only up
to ₹ 3000 for a day.
You cannot take a room more expensive than
this and if you also say that if the room
is of ₹ 5000 which you have liked and you
do not want to take that room of 3000, then
you say that you adjust 3000 in my policy,
which you have to adjust the claim and I will
give ₹ 2000 from my pocket.
Even if this will not work, then your treatment
will be done only if you are living in a room
of 3000 and this room is rent capping which
I came to know.
That the advisor from whom my father had taken
the policy, why hadn't he told it earlier
because they don't even tell?
And when your hospital then you understand
that there is capping here and the treatment
is also according to your capping, then all
the packages are made according to that and
people do not know this thing and you also
check it now whether your policy has capping.
Let's move on.
The second point is when you talk about ICU.
Look, in the ICU, the person is taken to the
emergency.
At that point, it is known that it happens
inside most policies that there is a capping
of 2% of the sum assured.
2% of Whatever your sum assured is, you may
have 1 day ICU room rent.
Meaning if you have a policy of 300000, then
₹ 6000 per day, then the company will not
pay more than it.
if you go to a big hospital on today's date,
forget that you will get an ICU bed for ₹ 6000
per day or per night.
You do not get it, then it is too much,
so you have to check that there is no capping.
Now let me tell you the third thing that
comes is
Automatic Restoration of Sum Assured now understands
this.
suppose you have a policy of ₹ 300000, now
what happens if you have a claim of rs 200000,
what will happen, Under most policies, you
will be told that now only ₹ 100000 is left.
Now you have 12 months.
If you took the policy money within January
and suppose your policy starts from January,
then you took the claim within January.
You took a claim of ₹ 200000 out of three
lakhs. You fell ill.
Now you think there are 11 months in a whole
year.
Now in these 11 months if I fall ill again,
what will happen.
nothing will happen.
In most policies, you will get only ₹ 100000
in this, then there is no restoration in it,
then you have to check whether there is automatic
restoration?
Now, what is the meaning of automatic restoration
that even if you fell ill and you took a claim
of ₹ 200000, then the next time when you
fall ill, you had the policy for ₹ 300000,
then you should get three lakhs sum assured
on it?
Now it is not in most policies.
Is it in your policy or not?
You check it.
Now this will blow the minds of 99% of the
people because most of the policyholders are
not aware of this restoration benefit, that
if something like this happens.
Let me give you an example of navy health
insurance.
In this, you get automatic restoration of
sum assured in Navy Insurance, then it is a major point.
Now let's move forward.
Now let's see the Accidental injury benefit.
Now, this is under very few policies.
You have to understand that.
You have taken a policy of ₹ 300000 means
you have a sum assured of ₹ 300000.
We take insurance so if later there is an accident,
If there is any mishap happen then, you don't have to
pay from your pocket.
If there is a bill of ₹ 500000 or ₹ 600000,
where will the rest of the money come?
In most of the policies, you have a sum assured
of 300000 then you will get the claim of only
three lakhs and you will have to pay the rest
of the money from your pocket.
At that time people did not understand how
to get money.
Then it is a stress for people and in such
a short time people feel that now we should
increase our policy, but it is not possible
practically.
You will get the claim for the sum assured.
But if there is a benefit in your policy that
your Sum Assured on Accidental Injury will
be 2X, then if there is the claim of six lakhs
instead of three lakhs, that will be passed and money
doesn't go out of your pocket.
You have to check it.
Now I said 99% in the last case, here in the
99.99% policies, there is no benefit of accidental
injury benefit.
Now you will ask where you get it, then you
will have to do a little research for it.
In short, I have researched for you that even
if you will study navy health insurance and
if you take your health insurance from the
navy, then you get accidental injury benefits.
So you can check I am just recommending you,
the rest is your choice.
Whatever you want to do, what you can do.
Now move ahead, any single occupancy room
means If you are single then what happens
if there is double occupancy inside the hospital
there are room lots in sharing too so if you
think that privacy matters to me and I need
a room for me many policies do not
have
coverage you should You have to check that
if you are alone and you need treatment for
yourself, then you get a private room, then
you should also check in your policy that
it should be there.
Now let's move on.
See this is the era of online.
This era has changed.
5 years ago people did not take online doctor
consultations.
Earlier people didn't know that Online consultation
can also be taken, but today's date, people
take online consultations with doctors.
It should be covered in your policies, You
are taking online consultation, you pay for
it, that should be covered.
People do not have enough time to go to the
doctor and when their number comes, it is
time waste that matters most on today's date.
People do not have much time.
So people can book online consultations according
to their convenience and people have to get
medical checkups done.
As you get your medical checkup done once a year,
then your medical checkup also costs money.
That too should be covered in your policy,
If you have taken any health insurance for
yourself, then whether it has this coverage
or not you check it.
Alright, let's move ahead.
you see here, you should find a claims relationship
manager here.
I have seen many people.
When they make the claim, they don't know
whom to talk to.
Now if you don't know who to talk to, it gets
very hectic for you.
If you are taking health insurance from whomever
and for example, If you are taking health
insurance from the navy, then you need a dedicated
claims relationship manager who will help
in getting your claim settled.
Whatever your hospital's bills come, all the
money should reach the hospital and the patient
who is there should get discharged.
This is the job of the claims settlement manager,
so here you will get the claims relationship
manager, he will help you.
You check whether you get any dedicated person
from where you have taken the policy.
Now, this is important.
Now let's assume that today you got a diagnosis
of a disease and the doctor said that we will
do the operation after 2 months, then the
doctor says that you come to get check every
week, come weekly and along with this you
get all these tests done and now you tell
me one thing, here, we understand that the
operation will take place after 2 months.
We get the money for the operation in our
health insurance claim.
We understand this, but I will go to the doctor
every week.
These days the tests are too expensive to
get the doctor checked, so will they go out
of my pocket?
This is the coverage, we call this, pre-hospitalization
coverage and it is pre mean you are getting
hospitalized, it is Before hospitalization
coverage.
Now understand the post-hospitalization coverage,
understand that you had an operation, After
that you have to take medicine.
There is also a test.
Again there is doctor consultation.
That too should be covered.
But in most policies, their timing is very
much less.
Suppose you have an operation, then it will
be covered only for 30 days.
You have to check for how long it is covered,
then I am telling you for example that pre-hospitalization
coverage should be for at least 2 months and
post hospitalization coverage should be at
least for 3 months because now If a disease
has been diagnosed, then, in reality, it is
operated after 2 months, then you do not have
to pay out of pocket and after the operation
or else you feel that you went to the hospital
and whatever treatment you got, then after
two or three months, if your treatment goes
on till then, where will its cost come from?
So that there will be no burden on your pocket,
you have to check that.
If you have taken health insurance, then you
should check it in your policy and if you
are going to take it next time, then check
it also, then go ahead.
Here, you see that it is also needed to get
the daycare retreatment.
Now let us understand what this daycare treatment
is, Now most of the policies in this you understood
that it is necessary to stay at night.
Meaning you have to spend 24 hours in the
hospital.
But today medical science has become very
advanced.
There are many operations such as hernia or
there are some laser operations in which the
doctor says that you have come in the morning
and I will discharge you in the evening.
But you should know that under most policies
if you do not stay at night in the hospital,
Then you will not get that expense.
So there the company also refuses to claim
that if you don't stay at night, otherwise
you will not get the expenses, then people
get stuck here, so here you have to check
that you are getting daycare treatment, then
check this out in your policy.
Now let's go ahead and understand what this
thing is now.
One is that I will go to the hospital and
get treatment and one is domiciliary.
What is it, that I am at home in this or a
person has got paralysis?
He can't go to the hospital.
Whatever treatment will be given to him now,
it will be at home.
Is this covered in your policy?
You would not have thought about it.
See, you are taking the policy.
If you are giving money to a company every
year, then you have to check that you should
get all these coverages, according to you.
You should get it according to me.
You check whether you need it or not because
these things are not as per the requirement.
Look we are taking health insurance for the
emergency, if any issue comes inside the emergency,
that should be covered.
At that time, the bank balance we have inside
our savings account doesn't affect it, this
is my opinion, so what do you think?
You can tell in the comment below.
Now you understand what organ donor coverage
means.
Let's assume that there is a girl and there
is an issue in her kidney and the doctor suggests
a kidney transplant.
Now if there is a kidney transplant, then
Suppose her mother agrees to give her kidney
to the girl who has taken the policy.
That 20-year old girl has taken the policy.
But she has taken the policy and if the mother gives her kidney now, then the mother will have to pay for her expenses.
Mother will also go to the hospital, she has
an operation, she will also get medicine,
she also has tests, then who will cover that
cost?
Mother herself will cover that cost, the answer
is no.
If you have taken medical insurance, then
you have to check that it is also necessary
to have organ donor coverage in it.
Are You Getting it?
Finally, There are a lot of expenses that
you have to check like whether the ambulance
coverage is there or not and there are many
things?
If I talk about that, then I will tell you
more than 20 points.
But I am telling the major things right now
that it is necessary to get all this coverage
and here you can see one more thing that it
is very important to get the no claim bonus
because it depends on the policy.
Some have 10%, Some have 20% and some have
50%.
Now, what is this?
The first thing is that it is probably not
even in some policies and where you do not
get any claim bonus, it is an issue.
Now, What does it mean, let me explain to
you?
Let's say you get no claim bonus of 50% in
any policy that means if you have taken any policy of ten lakhs.
You paid this year's premium but you did not
claim this year's claim.
What will happen next year is that you will
get a 50% bonus and this means that your policy
will be 15 lakhs instead of 1000000.
So every policy may not necessarily have 15%,
Whether 10% or 20% in a policy.
And it will be assumed that the higher the
no claim bonus, the more the premium increases,
then you will see it according to you.
I have given the example to explain to you
that if there is a policy of 100000 and there
is a no claim bonus of 10% then according
to 10% no claim bonus that if I have not taken
the claim this year, so in the next year,
my sum assured here, It will increase from
1000000 to 1100000 Now and next year it will
be of Rs 1200000, so now people will say that
if it increases accordingly, no matter how
much it will increase, then the answer is
no, that can only increase by one hundred
per cent basic.
This means if you have taken the police of
ten lakhs, If it will increase every year,
it will only go up to 20 lakhs.
That won't be 5000000 anytime now here I have
told you the basic things.
Now here if you feel that even these basic
things are not covered under your policy.
I am repeating this au feel that even the
basic points that I have told you are not
covered under your policy, then do not feel
bad but your policy is not that good either.
It is worthless then, you have to check all
these points.
Next time if you are taking the policy then
you need to understand that you are paying
for the policy and the money which you are
paying now, you are giving it from your earnings
and you are giving it because if there is
an emergency then no burden should not come
on me and if there is a burden, then it is
of no use.
Today I would like to tell you that like I
give you an example of Navy health insurance,
then if you have trust in insurance, whatever
is the benefit I have told you here, All these
points are covered.
The beginning of Navy is, If you have heard
the name of Sachin Bansal Ji who is the co-founder
of Flipkart and also the founder of Navy Health
Insurance, then here you are getting a very
big name, you are getting trust here.
If I talk about their hospital network, then
more than 10,000 hospitals come into their network
They are serving over 12 lakh customers.
Their claim settlement ratio is 97%.
Let me also tell you that if you are taking
a policy from anywhere then you must also
check the claim settlement ratio and if it
is less than 95% then it becomes a little concern.
So 97% of the industries are considered good
within the industry so that is the claim settlement
ratio of Navy Health Insurance.
Along with this, you can buy health insurance
for just ₹ 241 per month and it is a hundred
percent and you can avail yourself of cashless
claims in twenty minutes.
I will put a link in the description and comment
box starting at 241 rupees, and you can buy
health insurance.
Well, In this video I have tried to cover
major points which you should check Before
buying any Health Insurance.
How did you like this video?
You will let me know in the comment.
Lastly, if you still have any questions then
you can ask in a comment.
We will try to make the next videos on them.
If you are watching this video on Facebook
then follow and if you are watching on YouTube
then subscribe and click on the bell icon.
I Will See You In The Next Video, Link To
Navy Health Insurance Is In The Description
And Comment Box and go self-made